Hello English learners, welcome back to
another great lesson here at English Pod.
My name is Marco.
And my name is Catherine.
So Marco today, we've
got a little bit of an
unusual lesson because we're
talking about hypothetical situations.
Right, we're talking
about a unreal situation
or something that may
happen or may not happen.
Okay, so you're going to hear
all about this in today's dialogue.
We're going to hear
it a couple of times
when we come back,
we'll be breaking it down
for you so you know
all about these great
phrases and how to talk about
not real situations with your friends.
Okay, next question.
If Eric asked you out on a
date, what would you say?
Duh!
I would say yes.
Eric is the most popular kid in school.
Okay, my turn.
What would you do if you won the lottery?
Let's see.
If I won the lottery, I would buy
two tickets for trips around the world.
If you buy me a ticket,
I'll go with you for sure.
My dad would freak out if I
even mention a trip like that.
All right, this is a good one.
What would your mom say if you told
her that you're going to get married?
If I told her that, she would
faint and have me committed.
All right, so I think that was clear and
well, a very common situation, two teenage
girls talking to each
other about, you know,
boys and what would
you do and da da da?
Guys do this too.
So don't just put this on like girls, okay?
I don't think we do it like this though.
No, but it's actually a very
popular game in the car to play.
The what if game?
Yeah, exactly.
And that's exactly the
topic that we want to
talk about today is the structure, what
if, which is actually called a conditional?
All right, so conditional
because the results,
the thing that happens
depends on something else.
Exactly.
So let's actually take a
look at the words in today's
language takeaway before we
talk about all this grammar stuff.
Language takeaway.
Okay, so we'll start out
with some basic words.
Well, you know, they were talking about
guys and she said, if Eric asked you out.
Right, so to ask
somebody out, okay, so this
might be a little bit
strange because you
think, okay, to ask is
to ask a question, but
to ask out, it's a fixed
phrase and something
you say these two
words go together, right?
So I want to ask someone out.
I mean, I want to invite
someone on a date on
a romantic date, so
yeah, I want to ask him
out to dinner or he asked
me out to the movies.
Now, if I didn't want
to ask somebody out on
a romantic date, what would,
what, what would you use?
I'd say you could invite someone out, but
then again, it's always a little bit, well,
you can say invite for someone if
you're going to ask them on a date too.
So I'd say to ask out
is always romantic and
to invite can be
romantic or just friends.
Okay, so to ask somebody
out, now, they were
talking about other
situations, maybe they
would go on a trip or something,
and she said my dad would freak out.
This is a great phrase, this is something
that I used a lot when I was a teenager.
The word freak out.
Freak out.
So the verb to freak
out means to be really
angry or upset or, you
know, it could be a good
thing or a bad thing,
but usually when we're
talking about our
parents, it's a bad thing.
It's a bad thing.
So they get angry.
They start yelling at you.
Yeah, freak out.
Freak out means like overreact.
All right, and the last word that we have
on language takeaway today is committed.
Well, let's look at the whole phrase.
He says she would have me committed.
So this is actually being done to someone.
Now we did look at this
word before, but basically
for marriage, right, to
commit to somebody
to promise.
Yeah, but to have
someone committed means
that you're going to send them
away to maybe a mental institution.
Exactly.
So that means they have
psychological problems
and someone else
sends them to the hospital
because they can't send themselves.
Exactly.
So it's always used to
have someone committed,
right, because it's
being done to them.
They don't want it to happen.
It's involuntary.
Okay.
So she had him committed.
My mom's going to have me committed
if I keep working 20 hours a day.
Exactly.
So that's the way you use it.
So now you have another
way of using this verb.
But now I think we should
listen to this dialogue again.
We're going to slow
it down a little bit, and
then we'll come back and look at this
grammar focus that we want to talk about.
Next question.
If Eric asked you about on
a date, what would you say?
Duh, I would say yes.
What would you do if you won the lottery?
Let's see.
If I won the lottery, I would buy
two tickets for a trip around the world.
If you buy me a ticket, I
will go with you for sure.
My dad would freak out if I
even mention a trip like that.
All right, this is a good one.
What would your mom say if you
told her you were going to get married?
If I told her that, she would
faint and have me committed.
All right.
So we understood all the vocab now.
Now let's take a
look at these unreal
situations and what we
were saying, the what if game.
Right.
So I think it's important to push
these into two different categories.
We have one kind
where it's very unrealistic.
It's probably not going to
happen in that kind of situation.
And the other one is a
situation that could very
well happen, something
that's probably very common.
Okay.
So the first one we're
going to talk about is very
unrealistic situations, things
that probably won't happen.
Okay.
So let's take a look at an example
that we found in the dialogue.
The most common one,
and I think everybody gets
asked this question is if you won
the lottery, what would you do?
Okay.
If you won the lottery, so this is a
situation that's very uncommon, right?
Not many people in the lottery.
So we have to say, if
you won the lottery, do
we use this this this
verb in the past tense?
If you won the lottery, if this
happened, what would you do?
Right.
So Catherine, if you won the
lottery, what would you do?
If I won the lottery, I would buy a boat
and sail around the world with my friends.
All right.
So another example,
again, using the same
structure, right, the verb
in the simple past tense,
we would say, if you
were stuck on an island
with one other person,
who would that be?
All right.
So if you were stuck on a desert island
with one person, who would that person be?
So Marco, I'm going to
ask you, who would it be?
I think it would be an
engineer or a scientist
that could probably
get me off the island.
What about your girlfriend?
No, well, you know, that's the
point if I can get to her quicker.
Oh, okay.
I would say maybe kind of
romantic, but keep that kind of that.
So that's the first situation.
We've got these situations like being
stuck on an island, winning the lottery.
These are very unlikely.
But what about the other kind?
But before we move on to that, you notice
that we used the verb was, we didn't say if
I was on an island, I said, if
I were, right, or if you were.
So this is the way that
you're using in these
conditionals, if I were
you, or if you were
president of the United
States, and this is a rule.
So this is a grammar rule.
We're not going to describe why it happens
because it's very, very complicated.
You can look it up on our site, but
we're going to describe how to use it.
That's the most important.
So we can say, for example, Marco,
if I were you, I would die my hair red.
Why?
I don't know.
I don't think so.
So if I were you, I would, or if
you were me, what would you do?
Exactly.
So we always use it like this, right?
If you're going to use this conditional,
always use were for the subject.
Never was.
Right.
So you can tell, this is a
very, very big grammar issue.
A lot of English speakers make
this mistake very, very many.
So, but now you know
that you shouldn't make
this mistake and you
can speak properly.
All right.
So now that we've seen these
semi-unreal situations, let's move on.
We'll move on to something that's a little
bit more probable that it may happen.
Right.
So we've got these,
these situations that are
common or likely, for
example, in this lesson
we hear, I will go with you for sure.
So this is, if you buy me a ticket to
travel, of course, I will go with you.
So if you buy, this is in the
present tense, if you buy, then I will.
Right.
So now you notice the difference.
The verb is in the present and then
we use instead of wood, we use will.
So again, I can say, if it rains tomorrow,
I will stay home and watch TV all day.
Okay.
So think about this, we,
before we talked about
going to desert islands,
now we're talking
about rain and the weather,
they're very, very different.
The rain is, you know, is very common.
So we can say, if it rains
tomorrow, I will need an umbrella.
Mm hmm.
What about this, if we have
lunch tomorrow, what will we eat?
So okay.
So we have lunch pretty
much every day, right?
Yeah, pretty much.
So again, it's a, it's a
situation that is very probable.
So if we have lunch tomorrow, we will
probably eat, I don't know, pasta, I think.
Yeah.
And then like pasta.
Pasta.
Yeah.
Noodles.
All right.
So Marco, let's take
another listen to some
of these phrases and
try and figure out while
you're listening, which kind of
conditionality is first or the second.
Example one.
If it's sunny today,
we will go to the park.
Example two.
I would get a divorce if I were you.
Example three.
Mary will be very sad if Joe leaves.
Example full.
We wouldn't be so
late if Nick drove faster.
Very good.
For different
examples, and the first
conditional is the one that
we mentioned is very probable.
And the second conditional is
the one that's not so probable.
So they're very easy to distinguish.
You don't really need to know the names.
Just know how to use them, right?
Exactly.
And so just remember, if you
were me, what would you do?
We've got these kind of pairs,
these words that go together.
And the other one is more common.
It's if we, if it rains tomorrow,
I will bring an umbrella.
Perfect, so why don't we listen
to this dialogue for the last time?
Just to kind of reinforce
everything, and then
we'll come back and
talk a little bit more.
Okay, next question.
If Eric asked you out on a
date, what would you say?
Duh.
I would say yes.
Eric is the most popular kid in school.
Okay, my turn.
What would you do if you won the lottery?
See, if I won the lottery, I would buy
two tickets for a trip around the world.
If you buy me a ticket,
I'll go with you for sure.
My dad would freak out if I
even mention a trip like that.
All right, this is a good one.
What would your mom say if you told
her that you're going to get married?
If I told her that, she would
faint and have me committed.
So Marco, if we talk any
more about grammar,
someone's going to have
to have me committed.
It is a little bit
difficult to talk about
grammar, especially on
a podcast, because it's
such a difficult topic, and
it's also kind of heavy, right?
It is, but I'll tell you this.
These are very, very common
phrases, people to use these all the time.
We talk in hypotheticals very often, so if
you're asking for advice, for example, or
if you're just playing a game in the car,
you're going to encounter these, and it's
very important to be able
to know how to use them.
So, and this is what we want to see now,
please come to our website at EnglishPod.
com, and you have
a million questions.
You have a million hypotheticals that you
can leave on our website, so let us know.
Ask us the craziest, funniest,
weirdest questions that you can, right?
Exactly.
And if you have questions about the stuff
that we've been talking about, you're not
really clear on some
things, just ask us
because we're happy to answer your questions
and give more examples on the website.
Alright, so we'll see you guys
there, and until next time, bye!